<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the trew professors of Christes Gospell, inhabitinge in the parishe off Allhallowis, in Bredstrete in London, made by Thomas Sampson, sometyme their pastore</title>
            <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851686</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 665:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the trew professors of Christes Gospell, inhabitinge in the parishe off Allhallowis, in Bredstrete in London, made by Thomas Sampson, sometyme their pastore</title>
                  <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Joos Lambrecht?] at the signe of the golde[n] Bibell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at Strasburgh in Elsas [i.e. Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the moneth of Auguste. the yeare of our Lord. 1554.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title has "Brebstrete".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21683a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16975:1"/>
            <p>A letter to the trew profeſſors of Chriſtes Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / inhabitinge in the Pariſhe off Allhallowis / in Bredſtrete in London / made by Thomas Sampſon / ſometyme their Paſtore.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 6.</bibl>
               <p>¶ We as helpers therfore exhorte you / that ye receaue not the grace of God in vayne.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at Strasburgh in Elſas / at the ſigne of the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell / In the moneth of Auguſte. the yeare of our LORD. 1554.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:16975:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16975:2"/>
            <head>The grace a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fauour of God / our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / pourchaſed vnto vs / by the blody death of Chriſt our Sauiour / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felte and encreaſed in all your conſciences / too your euerlaſting conſolation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this age dothe not ſuffer me / my moſt louinge brethren / to come (as I wolde do) vnto you / and by talke &amp; brotherly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferringe / to putte you in mynde of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſte / which amongeſte woothers farre more worthie / euen I by Gods grace preached amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you. I therfore haue thought nedeful by theſe letters / now to do theſame / nowe I ſaye / when thoughe the peruerſe frowardnes of men / the trew preaching of Chriſtes Goſpel is banniſhed and mans doctrine is taughte with lyes &amp; fables: And thoughe ſome perchaunce will thinke that thys longeth not to me / but too hym that is youre Paſtore to doo / yet for as muche as once I was your paſtore / I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:16975:3"/>
not but teſtefye / that ſome pece of paſtorall cure dothe yet reſte in my harte towardes you. The whiche in dede dothe muche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me / as the preſente neceſſitie alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no les to require / to make a longe &amp; a large treatiſe / by whiche ye mighte haue an whole armour againſte all the aſſaultes off falſe Prophetes. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I conſider / how truly / and that with much dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ye haue ben taughte / and therewith thinkinge / that ye are not forgetfull hearers of the worde / I thinke that amonge you it ſhall ſuffice / if I do but name thoſe greateſt euelles / whiche nowe are poured forthe out of pulpittes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge you / and therewith put you in mynd of the truthe / contrary to theſe lyes / which once you both herde and recyeued / deſiring you to abide in the ſame. This will I do ſhortly / as I haue but littell / and theſame vnapte tyme to do it / yet truly I truſt to do it / as let Gods worde therein trye it. If firſt ye will ſuffer me to tell you / that throughe theſe fals Prophetes / the caſtell of youre healthe / the ſaluacion of your ſoules is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted / whome if ye ſuffer too be with you if ye yelde vp your ſelfes to the beleuinge &amp; folowing of their doctrine / then knowe ye that as by blynde lears ye be ledde / ſo you wyth them then beynge blynded / <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> ſhal wyth them fall in to the pitte of pardicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which
<pb facs="tcp:16975:3"/>
is prepared aſwell for the falſely ſeduced / as for the falſe ſeducer. Of thys I coulde be content to ſpeake the leſſe / but that I ſe that whyleſt of to many / and that Londy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / theſe beaſtes befolowed. Ye haue euen drawen and pulled vpon your heades thoſe abhominacions / whiche if but reaſon had ruled / ſhoulde not haue bene admitted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that by lawes they had ben thruſt vnto you / that I ſpeake not / what trew Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſhoulde haue moued you too haue done.</p>
            <p>Oh London / London / <note place="margin">An excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> London.</note> is this the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fruicte / to be the firſte / that withoute a lawe ſhouldeſt banniſh trew preaching out of the / too be the fyrſte that againſte lawes ſhalt admitte that maſſinge Idolatrie / to be the firſte that ſhall geue the example of ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to all Englande / whych ſhouldeſt yet haue bene the fyrſt in conſtancy / in humble / ſayeng for the continuinge of the truthe in the / in quiet and paciente ſuffringe for the truths ſake euen deathe / if by the rulers it had bene offered the. That grounde arte thou / whyche not in perſecucion / but before perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth doſt go backe / a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thou arte reſerued for the Lordes wofull cures / to whoſe iudgement London I leue the.</p>
            <p>Seing in Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe euels are receiued / as
<pb facs="tcp:16975:4"/>
it is nowe meete for vigilante Paſtors too watche ouer their flocke / to chaſe the wolf awaye / les at the Lordes hande they doo heare the name of hierlinges / <note place="margin">Ioan. 10</note> ſo nowe is it hygh tyme for you my louinge brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and all them that he the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God / to take heede whoſe voyce ye do heare / too beware of the leauen of papiſticall Phariſeis / and to kepe your ſelfes vndefiled from all their abhominacions.<note place="margin">The errour of tranſſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</note> The greateſt of whiche now I will reſite amonges all their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacions / one of the principall is their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of tranſſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the very pryde of papiſtrie / and the horrible offence / euen of the Turckes and Heathen. That a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſt / by his huſſing and buſſinge / and mumblinge vp of the woordes of Chriſte / more lyke a Coniuror then a Chriſtian / ſhoulde worke that miraculous alteracion and chaunginge of the ſubſtaunce of breade and wyne / into the ſubſtaunce of the bodye and bloude of Chriſte / whiche then is to be taken / as Chriſt hym ſelfe God and man / &amp; ſo to be adored. But you knowe my dere brethren / that there is no ſuche miracle too be beleued without the certayne doctrine of Gods worde to warant theſame / which the papiſtes can neuer ſhowe / &amp; therfore their miracle is not to be beleued / Chriſt in Inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuting the Supper / me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not to leaue there
<pb facs="tcp:16975:4"/>
hys body and bloud really and ſubſtancially as the papiſtes do teache: For Chriſte in the ſubſtaunce of hys body / was then to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified / he was to dye / he was to ryſe agayn / he was to aſcende / and he was / and in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame yet now is / to appeare before the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God / our Biſhop / aduocate / &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator / there ſo to remayne vntill the laſte daye / as the ſchriptures do teache. In the Supper he inſtituted a commemoration of the breaking of hys body / and ſheddinge of hys bloud / to be done and made of them that do eate that breade / and drynke of that cuppe / accordinge to hys inſtitution: which he called his body and bloude / for that it is to the receauers a ſeale and confirmacion of Chriſtes body broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and Chriſtes bloud ſhedde for them / that the profite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie thereof is theirs / whiche there do partake by fayth. And ſo theſe woordes: <hi>This is my body, and this is my bloud,</hi> are to be vnderſtand / and not as the tranſſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciators / literally enforce them. For their vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding / them is bothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus meaninge / and alſo to the office of hys body / beſydes that it is agaynſt the nature of hys very body. And that theſame phraſe of ſpeakinge is thus to be vnderſtanded / as I haue ſayde: The like phraſes in like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the ſcriptures dothe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly teche
<pb facs="tcp:16975:5"/>
vs. As whereof circumciſion / the LORD dothe ſaye: <hi>This is my couenaunt,</hi> where it was but the ſeale of the couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / as Paul calleth it. In the ſame ſorte it is ſayde: <hi>This is the pasouer. This cuppe is the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my bloud. Chriſt is the rocke.</hi> And in lyke maner are theſe to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. So that if the aduerſaries will geue the / geue the holy Ghoſte leaue to expound hym ſelf / then theſe woordes. <hi>Thys is my body? Thys is my bloud? are figuratiuely to be vnderſtanded.</hi> As the leke Phariſeis are / and ſo ſerue they not all for their mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruus tranſſubſtanciation.<note place="margin">The ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the maſſe.</note> The ſecond ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominacion is their ſacrifice of the maſſe. In whiche (too let many thinges paſſe / as the ſtraungenes of the tounge / the Ieweſh apparel / the fonde noddes / croſſes / beckes &amp; duckes.) Thre euels moſte notable and to a Chriſtian conſcience intollerable are there. Firſte their wicked ſacrifice / <note place="margin">Thre abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in the ſacrifice off the popiſhe maſſe.</note> whiche their maſſeboke teſtefieth / to be Propiciatorie / to take awaye the ſynnes of all thoſe / be they dead or liuing / for whom thei do ſay maſſe: Yea / profitable and availeable for warres / peace / wether / ſickenes / for murrain of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes / and for whatſoeuer ye luſt to bye their appliecacion. Oh ſhameful blaſphemie. As concerninge the ſacrifice Propiciatorie for ſynne / ye muſt hold the anker of your faith
<pb facs="tcp:16975:5"/>
that this ſacrifice Chriſt him ſelf once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all in his own bloudy death. He was the prieſt &amp; the ſacrifice / the offerer and the thing offered / &amp; by his own bloudy offering purified he in the ſhedding of his bloude all hys fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne. By it purchaſed he eternall ſanctificacion &amp; ſaluacion for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhalbe ſaued: &amp; by it finiſhed he for euer / the ful pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piciacion for ſynnes:<note place="margin">Math. 27</note> for ſayeng theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des it is fyniſhed or conſummate / he yelded vp the ghoſte. Deteſtable therfore is the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall ſacrifice &amp; ingerous to the bloudy death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Chriſt inſtituted this ſupper to be a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to vs / and not that of it a prieſt ſhould make a propiciatory ſacrifice for ſynne: In the eating &amp; drinking of it / that we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare the Lordes death / offeringe the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thankes therefore (and therefore is it called of the fathers a ſacrifice of thankes) and not leauinge any more ſacrifice propy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatorie for ſynne too anye prieſte too offer:<note place="margin">Euchariſtia</note> That we eatynge and drinkynge / according too hys inſtitucion / ſhoulde by fayth applie vnto oure conſciences / the benefite of hys deathe and paſſion / and not geuinge power too any prieſte by meſſing too applie the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of hys death / to whome and to what he lyſteth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16975:6"/>
               <note place="margin">The Lords ſupper ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not for one dead.</note>Chriſt ordeined hys Supper neither for the dead / whiche haue no vſe of eating and drinking with vs in the congregacion: nor yet for beaſtes / wether / nor war / for which Chriſt did not dre: but for hys church liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon thys earth / that nedeth hys worde / &amp; nedeth hys Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firminge of their fayth.</p>
            <p>☞ Thus plainly / ye ſe one miſcheuous miſuſe in this maſſe. The ſeconde euell is / that the bread and cuppe (which the Lorde inſtituted too be receaued of the faythefull with thankes geuinge) In their maſſe they do abuſe / and make of it an Idol / holding it vp for the people / not onely to gaze vppon / but to geue vnto it that honor / whiche is dewe vnto God alone: And ſo bothe make of it an Idol / and of the people groſſe Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors / and tranſgreſſers of Gods commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement. The fylthines of which Idolatrie / I know you do ſe ſo plaine / that I nede not with many woordes to impugum it / for a Chriſtian conſcience can not but abhorre it. The thirde euel is that in their maſſe / that that is eaten and drounken is done &amp; deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of the prieſt all alone / with quartering and ſoppinge / with lickinge and ſuppinge / with waſſhing and wyping / and ſuch prety trickes of their owne inuenting. Chriſte in hys inſtitucion apoynteth thys ſupper too
<pb facs="tcp:16975:6"/>
he ſelebrate of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Math. 26 Mar. 14. Luc. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Take ye, and drynk ye all of this ſayeth he: This do ye in remembraunce of me.</hi> For ſo oft as ye eate this bread / and drinke of this cup ye ſhew the Lordes death tyll he commeth. Chriſt and Paule ſpeaketh not to the prieſt alone / but too the whole congregacion / too obſerue thys ordinaunce of eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge at the Lordes ſupper: Whereby ye maye playnely ſe how contrary thys doyng of our popiſhe maſſers is in this alſo to the Inſtitucion of Chriſte.<note place="margin">The maſſe of all Idoles moſte abhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable.</note> And too be ſhorte in thys their whole maſſe is nought / els but an horrible prophanacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: Wherefore as a moſte iniurius blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye / too the bloude of Chriſte / as a moſte groſſe Idolatrie / as a moſte wicked propha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion of Chriſtes inſtitucion / of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is this maſſe to be eſchewed and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred.</p>
            <p>Out of his miſcheuous Idol the maſſe / form they vnto the people / a new founde ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of their owne inuentinge: deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the people (as they ſaye) through the miracle of their tranſſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a body / in which body / becauſe alſo there is bloude therefore / they do not miniſter their conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated cup accordingly / for feare of ſpilling and yet they geue drinke too their houſeled to waſhe doune the cromes withall. Oh
<pb facs="tcp:16975:7"/>
theues where learne ye too miniſter ſuche a ſacrament. Where haue ye your ground in the ſcripture for this / your vnholſome hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell. Who can with a good conſcii<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce receyue ſuche a new found Popiſh ſacramente at a papiſtes hande / ſeynge alſo it is thereto off them vſed / to put Chriſtes true inſtitucion out of hys trew vſe. Whoſe appointed ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce is that the bread of thankesgeuing / and the cuppe of thankesgeuing ſhoulde be eaten and droncken of the congregacion / as before I ſayd.</p>
            <p>Thys their newe founde Sacrament they hange vppe in the pix / they carrye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be adored / with many ſuch miſchiefs of their owne inuentinge / whiche to reken vp / all were an endles la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.<note place="margin">The papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes defende their doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vvith manacinge vvordes, vvith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vvith fyre and faggot, vvith axe and halter. The doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted of the papiſtes</note> I leaue them therfore euer liſteninge when I may heare them defende theſe their abhominacions by the written woorde off God / but this as they neuer yet coulde do / ſo ſhall they neuer be able to do it / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of all Chriſtians are they wiſh their euaſyons to be forſaken.</p>
            <p>In the doctrine of Iuſtificacion they wander enwrapped in laberin theſe inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable. They erre in extenuating ſynne bothe originall and actuall / in not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the lawe / the force of it (I meane) nor
<pb facs="tcp:16975:7"/>
the ende of it / in makynge a Iuſtification / partly of Chriſtes grace / partelye of mans free wil / good mocyons and good worckes / and herein they ſo enwrappe theym ſelfes with their termes of the fyrſt grace / <note place="margin">Toyes for an ape too play vvith all.</note> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde grace / grace preſidente / grace conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatinge / grace folowinge / with merite of congruence / and merite of condignitie / that neither vnderſtande thee trewe iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / neither canne other men vnderſtande what they do meane by their Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But their doctrine is too bringe men into a continuall doubtynge of ſaluacion / and leadeth them cleane from that free Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion / whiche we haue in Ieſus Chriſte. But you my brethren haue out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures receyued / and I truſte by the practy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of youre owne conſcyences haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
            <p>☞ That by nature ye are the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath of your ſelfs: as of your ſelfs that ye are but ſuche a lompe of ſynne / that in you dwelleth no good thynge. For whyche the lawe iuſtely condempneth you as gilty of Goddes curſe and wrathe / and ſo dryueth you too Chriſte. By whoſe grace ye be frely iuſtified.</p>
            <p>By whoſe bloudde ſheddynge / onely and alone / the attonemente is nowe made
<pb facs="tcp:16975:8"/>
made betwene God and you / whiche you beleuing are made the heires of bleſſinge / of whiche your conſciences by fayth beinge aſſured by the worke of Gods ſpirite / <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> ye be at peace with God / becauſe ye do feale euen in your hartes by liuelye perſwaſion off fayth / that Chriſt hath loued you / and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hym ſelf for you / <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> for whoſe onely ſake ye are iuſtefied and ſaued: Which you thus felinge / are ledde by theſame ſpirite that worketh thys in you too render vnto God the ſacrifice of your body / in liuing &amp; doing thoſe workes / which in hys ſight are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table / and that in a fredom and libertie off the ſpirite / I meane no fleſhely libertie / but that libertie of the ſpiritie / by whiche we darre drawe nye vnto the ſeate of Goddes grace / calling hym: Abba father / that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that ſubdueth the libertie of the fleſhe / and maketh it captiue &amp; bonde too ſerue the ſpirite. In which you alſo walkinge / when ye haue done all that ye can do / yf ye coulde do all that is commaunded you too do / yet ſeinge all mans righteouſnes is but as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled clothe / ye ſeke not thereby the perim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of your Iuſtificacion. Which is all redy fully geuen you in Chriſtes Ieſus / ye loke not to the merite of your good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: but on your part knowing your owne want and imperfection / <note place="margin">Luc. 17.</note> yea / and ſynne eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:16975:8"/>
in the beſt ye do / ye ſaye: we are vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruauntes commending all your doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the grace of God thorowe Chriſte / that by hym they maye be made pure: on Godes parte conſidering / that the good ye do / is the worke of his ſpirite in you / which worketh in all men / bothe to will &amp; to do / ye do geue vnto hym the glory / ſeyng by his grace onely / ye are that good that ye are. Neuertheles / yet this alſo ye knowe that the Lord / <note place="margin">Good vvor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note> whiche through Chriſte hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted you vnto his grace / doth of the ſame grace in Chriſte / accept theſe youre workes into hys fauour / as iuſt perfect and good. Whiche though they be the woorkes of hys ſpirite in you / yet is he content to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called and eſtemed as yours / and as youres dothe he of hys owne fre grace reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe in this lyfe / and in the lyfe to come. In this that I haue thus ſpoken / you ſe the force of ſynne originall and actuall / the force and ende of the lawe / the power of mans free will / the trew iuſtification / ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s regeneracion / and the life / fruictes &amp; perfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of Gods regenerate chylde: By which ye may the more eaſely perceaue how farre the papiſtes wander from the truthe of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification / by which they drawe men into a deſperate doubting of ſaluacion / whyche who ſo liketh / let them taſte therof. Here is
<pb facs="tcp:16975:9"/>
occaſion alſo geuen me to warne you of all thoſe meanes that they haue taught too be meritorius to deſerue Gods grace / as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of ſuperrogacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / workes done of a good entent / fiſh faſtes / vowes / pylgrimages / par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dons / <note place="margin">Conterfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts good vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</note> and ſuche like Popiſh traſhe / which though as yet perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they dare not tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / yet haue they taught / and will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teache it. But againſt all ſuch / I acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt you ſufficiently armed / if ye holde faſt thys that our onely merite a valiable before god / is the merite of Chriſt / whiche he frely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth / and God for his onely ſake frelye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth to all trew beleuers / which is vnto them full perfyt / and ſufficient merit / righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes / ſanctification / &amp; ſaluacion.<note place="margin">The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of ſainctes.</note> They teache alſo inuocacion of ſainctes / to make them mediators / if not too God for vs / yet vnto Chriſte to ſpeake the better for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note>The ſcripture teacheth playn / that betwen God and man / there is but one mediator / the man Ieſus Chriſt / who therfore became man / that for men he alone ſhould make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as for mans rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion he alone did dye.<note place="margin">Ioan. 15</note> Wherefore euen he alſo teacheth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father in hys name / promiſing to ſuche that they ſhall be harde.<note place="margin">Prayer abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed amonge the papiſtes 1. Cor. 14</note>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer abuſe they not onely in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tonge / contrary to the doctrine of Paule / whiche will haue all thinges done in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregacion
<pb facs="tcp:16975:9"/>
/ to the edifyeng thereof: in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticious numbring of a certayne number of Pſalmes / or Pater noſters / of whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the people ſhalbe ſure / <note place="margin">Math. 6</note> they teache the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of beades / contrarye vnto whiche Chriſt our Sauiour taught / condemninge it as a phariſeicall ſuperſticion / when for their much clatering ſake / they thinke them ſelfes to be hard:<note place="margin">Prayenge for the dead</note> But alſo they teache and defend prayeng for the dead / to be charitable and propiciatory.<note place="margin">Apoc. 14</note>
            </p>
            <p>Where as yet the ſcripture teacheth / that they that dye in the Lorde / are inſolace and bleſſednes. As then they nede not our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / ſo our prayers can adde noughte vnto their bleſſednes:<note place="margin">Avvaie vvith ioure purgatorij rakers, and four maſſes of Requſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> And on the contrary parte they that dye wickedlye / haue no remedye euerlaſtingly: So that on all partes / thys kynde of prayer is in vayne. The wother being in moſte bleſſed ſaftie / and with theſe the tyme of health &amp; grace beinge paſt / theyr curious charitie therfore / and their peuiſhe propiciatorye prayer hath no ground in the ſcriptures. But through this they haue pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the purſe of many a poore man / for on thys vnhappye grounde buylde they chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries / trentalles vniuerſaries / diriges / pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory / pardons for ſoules departed / and a pece of their expiatory ſacrifice / with many ſuche proper deuiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16975:10"/>
               <note place="margin">Auriculer confeſſion.</note>Auriculer confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they teache / in which they enforce a numbring of ſynnes / whiche is nought / els but the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome / and as they vſe it a killing of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſciences / and hath no grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. In an anguiſhe and dute of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is both good / neceſſary / and comfortable / for a man to counſail with ſum ſuche lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned elder / in whoſe lippes dothe lye the law of truthe. Agayne / if the trew eccleſiaſticall diſcipline were vſed / a pece of it oughte too be / that the man reſtored / ſhoulde of hys faulie make an open confeſſion before the congregacion / to declare publicquely hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce. Yea / and a miniſter may vppon iuſt grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de examine any / of whom he hath cure / of ſuch a faute / as he ſeeth him worth to be reproued for: But this is ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eareſhrifte / that a man moſte blynde / maye eaſely iudge thereof.<note place="margin">Popiſſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencions.</note> But the rable of their errors are to many now to recite / as of the authoritie of the churche / of the not erring of the churche / of diſcipline / of theyr fyue new enuented ſacrament / of voues / of ckoyſe of meates / of images / and ſuch lyke. Againſt all / whiche that ye maye be armed my deare brethren / I require you not onely to call to minde the doctrine of the truthe receyued. But alſo that for the triall of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye do abyde in the worde of the truthe / Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:16975:10"/>
worde I meane. And becauſe / here they haue alſo an error / I will but recite it / and ſo make an ende.<note place="margin">Tradicions</note>
            </p>
            <p>Their error is / that Gods writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worde is not a ſufficiente doctrine vnto ſaluacion / but (ſay they) the voyce of the church / tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions / and counſayles are to be harde of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. As for tradicions / there is no tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any matter of faithe to be receyued / other then is in the ſcriptures expreſſed. Likewiſe doctors and counſailles / <note place="margin">Doctors. Counſails. Cuſtomes. Note.</note> with the conſent and cuſtome of the churche / are ſo farre to be harde in matters of faithe / as they do agre with the writen ſcripture: for it is the touche ſtone to trye them all by / &amp; that in ſuche ſorte / that if they ſaye not / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this woorde / then as there is no light in them / ſo are they not to be folowed.<note place="margin">Eſa. 8.</note> As for tradicions / cuſtomes / <note place="margin">Ceremonies</note> and by and for the order of the churche ceremonies recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vſed / which be no matters of faith / they may be admitted and altered at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecion of theym that haue the rule of the church vnder Chriſt / according to the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſite of the tyme / and the diſpoſition of the people / ſo that in them be nothinge elles but trew edifying to vnfayned Godlynes. And ſuche are of the people with humblines too be receyued. But for the ful triall of ſuche / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea / and for the full and perfect inſtitucion
<pb facs="tcp:16975:11"/>
of all men / in ſuche thinges as concerning ſaluacion / God hath lefte vnto his church and people hys written worde.<note place="margin">The holy ſcripture is a ſufficient doctrine for oure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvritte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites. Ioan. 20.</note> In whiche though all thinges that God mighte haue cauſed to be written / be not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet in it ſo much is written / as ſufficeth to teache vs that Ieſus Chriſt is the ſonne of God / and alſo that we beleuing / might haue lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge / as Ihon dothe witnes / by whiche we learne / that the written worde of God. is a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctrine to inſtruct vs in that fayth / whiche bringeth to lyfe euerlaſtinge. It is that ſufficient doctrine that can alone make men learned vnto ſaluacion / by the fayth which is in Chriſt Ieſus / it alone ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth to make the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God perfectly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed too all that is good / as witneſſeth Paule.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3 Ioan. 5. Luc. 16. 2. Pet. 1.</note> Therefore vnto the ſcriptures do Chriſte ſende the Phariſeis / Abraham too Moyſes and the Prophetes / Peter alſo to theſame worde of the Prophetes / as to the doctrine that ſufficeth to enſtructe vs too ſaluacion. The knowledge of whiche worde whoſoeuer goeth aboute to take from the people by putting it into a ſtraunge langage to the ende that the more ſafely / our popiſh marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes maye kepe their marte of fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and Popery / he robbeth the people of their meane to ſaluacion / he openith a dore for theues and murtherers / to deuoure the
<pb facs="tcp:16975:11"/>
flocke of Chriſt / and if at the worldes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / he ſuſtayneth not the iudgemente of a thefe / yet at Godes hande ſhall he be ſure to haue the iudgement of a ſoule murtherer.</p>
            <p>☞ Thus briefly I haue put you in mynd my deare brethren of the principall errors of the aduerſaries / and of the truthe contrary to them / not ſo copiouſly as the matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth / but ſhortly meaſuring the neade of your knowledge / for I haue not to do now with the ignorant / but with you / of whom by the tyme and kynde of your teachinge / I iudge that ye be able not onely too iudge off the truthe / but too be brotherly enſtruetors of other in theſame. And thus I haue done furſt to exorte you conſtantly to abide in the truthe receyued.<note place="margin">Continuan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in the truth</note> Call to youre mynde that God of his great mercy and goodnes hathe long ben in planting / ſowing / and watering of you / as it were to make you a garden off pleaſure vnto hym ſelfe. Theſe ſedes of lyfe the deuel by hys doctors will now go about to picke out of your hartes. But if in thys Goſpelling adge / ye haue bene worthy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Goſpel / if with the worde herde with youre eares / the Lordes ſprite hathe touched your hartes to beleue the worde of truthe preached / as he hath done to ſo many as haue vnfaynedly deſired it / <note place="margin">Ioan. 10</note> if ye be the ſhepe / which haue rightely herde the ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes
<pb facs="tcp:16975:12"/>
voyce / then ſurely the ſtraungers ſupplanting voice ſhall ye not heare / but ye ſhall flee frome ſuche hurelinges / as frome theues / robbers and murtherers. Hereby verely ſhall ye be knowen what ground ye are / fruteful / or vnfruteful conſtant / or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the tyme:<note place="margin">The proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of good goſpelers.</note> Good Goſpel hearers be not ſuche as will be toſt aboute with euery wynde / they be no ſuche grounde as wil be dried vp with euery blaſt of bourning heate / but they abide in Godes truthe / ſerchinge and learninge theſame in hys holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / and that with ſuche faithfull diligence and conſtante obedience / that if an aungell from heauen ſhal preache an other Goſpel / they holde hym accurſed:<note place="margin">Galat. 1.</note> Yea / and thoughe there be many counterfaicie Chriſtians / that fall awaye frome the Lordes truthe / yet abide they with Chriſte and ſaye:<note place="margin">Ioan. 6. Heare and kepe the vvorde off god.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hafte the wordes of euerlaſting lyfe:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider my deare brethren / that not too heare alone / but to kepe Chriſtes woorde maketh a man happie. And in kepinge the principall parte is too perſeuer in the doctrine off truthe / thys maketh Chriſtes diſciples / this maketh you free / yea / thys is it / that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man ſafe / for he that perſeuereth too the ende / ſhalbe ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10</note>Thys alſo haue I written too exorte you / to kepe your ſelfes vndefiled frome all
<pb facs="tcp:16975:12"/>
Popiſhe leauen / <note place="margin">Note and bevvare.</note> yf ye do fall from the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell / and embrace Poperie / ye fall frome truthe to lyes / frome the woorde of lighte and lyfe / to darkenes and death / frome ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion to dampnacion / from God too the deuell.<note place="margin">Luce. 11.</note> Ye are then they / into whome the euell ſprete reentreth with ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe then hym ſelfe / ye are then the foliſhe buylders whiche ſuffer the vnrecouerable ruin. And as then with that filth that is in Popery / ye be defyled with it: ſo of the dampnacion whiche is due to ſuche abhominacion / ye ſhall be partakers of it.<note place="margin">Chriſtes death &amp; the Popiſh Maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe can not agre toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> But if ye thinke that ye can bothe embrace Popery and the Goſpel / ye do diſceaue your ſelfes / for you can not bothe holde the taſte off Chriſtes deathe in your conſciences / and alowe alſo that maſſe / whiche is the defacer of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes deathe / you can not embrace the righte vſe of the Lordes ſupper / and alſo vſe and partake the horrible prophanacion of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame: Ye can not by faythe apprehende free iuſtificacion / and yet ſeke by your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and merites too be ſaued: you can not accepte Godes written woorde / as the ſufficient doctrine of ſaluacion: and alſoo take mans doctrine and tradicions / as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to theſame / and ſo forthe of the reſt. This can ye not do bothe / they are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16975:13"/>
               <note place="margin">Serue God accordinge to his vvor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.</note>But if ye coulde do it / yet may ye not do it / for God will none of your ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geled ſeruice / for as there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene Chriſte and Beliall / ſo men muſt not halte on both ſydes in Godes ſeruice / but eyther ſay that God is God / or els that Baal is god.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 3. Reg. 18</note> God neuer allowed that ſeruice of the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines / whiche both ſerued their Idols / and worſhipped the lyuing God. But if ye be turned to the Lord / then all ſtraunge Gods muſte ye cleane forſake. The Lorde is God alone / alone therfore according to hys worde will he be ſerued.<note place="margin">Exod. 20</note> God is ouer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gelious God / wherefore he will haue whole man wholy to be hys alone / as our fyrſt comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement teacheth vs. Agayne / if you thinke that in your hartes ye will ſerue the Lord / but yet ye will be and may be preſent in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at their Idolatrie.<note place="margin">Fleſhlij pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecie.</note> For your hart ſhalbe in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is but a fleſhly policie / which fayleth as many as truſt vnto it.<note place="margin">The maſſe is an vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thefe.</note> How can you / too whome Chriſtes deathe is deere: abyde to ſe that whoriſh thefe / that ſtealeth from Chriſte the glory of his death. Howe can ye / which haue ben and are ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue with thankefulnes the Lordes ſupper according to Chriſtes inſtitucion / abide to ſe the horrible prophanacion thereof?<note place="margin">Harte and mouth muſt go together in matters of God.</note> And ſo forth of the reſt. But if your conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were ſuche that ye coulde thus do / yet knowe ye
<pb facs="tcp:16975:13"/>
thys / that it is againſte your Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> For we are taughte / that too beleue with the hart / &amp; to confeſſe with the mouth maketh a man ſafe. Bothe hartes belefe / &amp; mouthes confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt go together / whiche dothe not ſo in you / when inwardly ye are Goſpelers / &amp; outwardly deſſemblers with papiſtes. Ye are bought with a pryce (ſayeth Paule) glorify now God in your body and in your ſprite / whiche are Gods.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> Seinge both body an ſprite are Goddes / not onelye by creacion / but bought alſo by redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / euen in the price of Chriſtes bloude / ye can not with a diſſembling prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / couple your bodies with papiſtes / for then ye do not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in your bodies. We rede not that any chylde of God / vſed euer iuſtlye anye ſuche diſſimulacion.<note place="margin">Examples of conſtanci in goddes vvorde. dan. 6.14 Dan. 3.</note> Daniel vſed none ſuch and therfore was he ſone accuſed of not ado<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the kyng / Bel and the Dragon. The thre chyldren / whether they came by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion / or came of their owne mynde / where the Idol was / diſſembled not / for forth with they were accuſed as tranſgreſſors of the kynges commaundement. Eleazarus wold not diſſemble / eating euen of lawful fleſhe.<note place="margin">2. mach. 6</note> Theſe men glorified God in body &amp; ſprite / theſe men beleued in hart / &amp; confeſſed with the mouth / &amp; ſo muſt you do / without any other muyſinge / yf ye will do the office off
<pb facs="tcp:16975:14"/>
Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Of offence geuinge. Note vvel.</note> And this to do not onely the profeſſion of Chriſtianitie enforceth / but Chriſtian cheritie alſo. Our doinges muſt be without offence geuinge: But by thys diſſembling a double ſtomble blocke is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche euen in thinges indifferent is to be auoyded. For what though a Chriſtian may eate frely of meates offered vnto Idols / yet if thereby an Idolater / whoſe conſcience in hys ſuperſticion / ſhoulde be confirmed ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by / it were better neuer to eate fleſhe. And what though al thinges be clean to the clean to be eaten on all dayes with thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing / yet better it is not to eate fleſh / nor to drinke wyne:<note place="margin">Rom. 14 1. Cor. 8</note> then too offende thereby thy weake brother:<note place="margin">Note ye diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſemblinge goſpelers.</note> If this be to be obſerued in thinges indifferente / howe muche more in thinges which are abſolutely euell / muſt ye take heede that neither ye geue occaſion off concerninge the conſcience of an Idolatrie / nor yet of offending the weke to draw them to the leeke euell with you: bothe whiche ye do / when bothe a papiſt and a weke brother ſeeth you as mingrels myngling your ſelfs with the Papiſtes in their Idolatrie. As muche might I ſpeake / howe that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that ye do in the congregacion muſte be done to edifyeng.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14</note> But of this to haue full inſtruccion.<note place="margin">Caluine.</note> I referre you to the mynde off mayſter Caluine / lately tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated &amp; printed
<pb facs="tcp:16975:14"/>
in Engliſh. Thus now I ende wiſhing you all well in the Lorde.<note place="margin">Godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations.</note> Abide in hys truthe / kepe your ſelfes vndefiled. Offer youre ſelfes hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly to ſuffer all violence of bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye lawes for the truthes ſake / kepe ſafe your conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / thoughe the ſworde taketh your lyues from you / ſuffer &amp; beare withal humblenes and quiet obedience. Humble your ſelfes in vnfayned repentaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde / in the horrible plague of Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pery / that of hys mercy he maye be moued to ende theſe dayes of deluſion / and let your prayers alwayes aſcend vp before the Lord / begginge of hym ſuche thynges as ye nede. In which I beſech you to praye alſo for me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Youre louinge frend and orator. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Sampſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>The grace of our LORD Ieſus Chriſt be with you all. AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
